A Guide to the James E. Copeland Scrapbooks, 1892-1925; nd
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
James E. Copeland Scrapbooks 1892-1925; nd
Thomas Balch Library
M 070
This collection contains photocopies of fourteen of numerous scrapbooks created throughout his life by James E. Copeland. Topics vary from drama, literature and moral issues to general history, the American Civil War and historical figures. There is some duplication of articles among the scrapbooks held by Thomas Balch Library and not all photocopies are complete. Partial indexes for each volume are included. The original scrapbooks, held by the family, are in fragile condition; best copies were made at the time the collection materials were donated.
James E. Copeland family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
James E. Copeland family
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2011.0279X
Biographical Information
The Copeland family settled in the Hillsborough (herein after Hillsboro) area in 1765 when David and Deborah Copeland built a family farmhouse. Their son James Copeland expanded the farmhouse in 1804. Several generations later, James Edward Copeland (1845-1937) was born in Hillsborough, Loudoun County, Virginia. Copeland served as a private in the 35th Virginia Cavalry Battalion, Company C for which service he and his wife, Fannie V. Copeland (1859-1950), received Confederate pensions. Although an outspoken critic of public schools Copeland started his career as a teacher in the first Hillsboro public School in 1870. He received an MD from Washington University School of Medicine, Baltimore, Maryland in 1876 and commenced his medical practice in Rectortown, Fauquier County, Virginia where he met and married in 1881, his wife Fannie V. Copeland. Copeland practiced medicine from 1877 to 1925 when a kick in the elbow from a horse ended his career. He had two children, Edward Virgil Copeland (1882- 1918), also a physician who joined his father in his practice until his untimely death from influenza, and Maria A. Copeland (1886-1969) a teacher in Round Hill. The family is buried in the Hillsboro Cemetery.
J. E. Copeland was an enthusiastic recorder of historical events and was known as the historian of Hillsboro. A large collection of scrapbooks, still held by the family, attest to this lifelong interest in recording events.
Scope and Content
This collection contains photocopies of fourteen of numerous scrapbooks created throughout his life by James E. Copeland. Topics vary from drama, literature and moral issues to general history, the American Civil War and historical figures. There is some duplication of articles among the scrapbooks held by Thomas Balch Library and not all photocopies are complete. Partial indexes for each volume are included. The original scrapbooks, held by the family, are in fragile condition; best copies were made at the time the collection materials were donated.
Arrangement
Box: folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
American Civil War Medicine & Surgical Antiques: Dr. James E. Copeland: http://www.braceface.com/medical/Articles/Copeland_James_E.htm accessed 11/15/2011.
Loudoun Cemetery Index - search on Copeland - accessed 2-8-2012.
Savitt, Todd L., "James E. Copeland: A Country Doctor in and Age of Medical Change," Virginia Cavalcade, Volume 23, #1, Summer 1973, pp.10-17.
Scheel, Eugene, Loudoun Discovered: Quaker Country and the Loudoun Valley Vol. 4. Leesburg, VA: Friends of the Thomas Balch Library, 2002.
Scheel, Eugene, Loudoun Discovered: Waterford, The German Settlement and Between the Hills, Vol. 5. Leesburg, VA: Friends of the Thomas Balch Library, 2002.
Scheel, Eugene, The History of Loudoun County, Virginia: Hillsboro, Virginia - 200Years Later http://www.loudounhistory.org/history/hillsboro.htm, accessed 2-9-2012.
U S, Confederate Pensions, 1884-1958, AncestryLibrary.com, accessed 11/15/ 2011.
U S Civil War Soldier Records and Profiles, AncestryLibrary.com, accessed 11/15/2011.
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
Copeland, Dr. J. E., Hillsborough and its Picturesque Environs. (Leesburg, VA: Loudoun Times Mirror), 1926 VREF 975.528 COP; Savitt, Todd L., "James E. Copeland: A Country Doctor in and Age of Medical Change," Virginia Cavalcade, Volume 23, #1, Summer 1973, pp.10-17; Ann Thomas Research Papers, 1836-2005 (M030); and Copeland, Edward Virginia, Notes on Round Hill, October 2001 (Unpublished Papers.)
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1903-1910
  - Scrapbook 3, 1903-1907
  - Scrapbook 4, 1908-1912
  - Scrapbook 5, 1911-1912 with some earlier dates
  - Scrapbook 6, 1913-1914
  - Scrapbook 7, 1892-1893, editorials from the Baltimore Sun
- (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 8, 1914-1915
  - Scrapbook 9, 1914-1915 and Civil War information
  - Scrapbook 10, not dated
  - Scrapbook 12, Cultural information: Poetry, Drama, Moral Issues
  - Scrapbook 17, 1910-1919
- (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 18, 1918-1920
  - Scrapbook 21, April-October 1920
  - Scrapbook 34, 1924-1925